Guide to the John Pitkin Norton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Pitkin Norton papers
1837-1852
MS 367
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.29
(8 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, writings and other papers of John Pitkin Norton, professor of agricultural chemistry at Yale from 1846-1852. Norton's diaries contain among other topics Norton's observations on slavery and abolition, the Amistad case, the Liberty Party, religion and temperance. Professor Norton was also closely associated with the early days of the Sheffield Scientific School and was a pioneer in the application of scientific principles and methods to agriculture.
Norton, John Pitkin, 1822-1852
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Special Files.
Biographical / Historical
John Pitkin Norton was born July 19, 1822, in Albany, New York, the son of John Treadwell Norton, a successful farmer, and Mary Hubbard (Pitkin) Norton. He decided at an early age that he, too, would become a farmer. His father agreed to this idea on condition that he receive a thorough education to prepare him for this pursuit. Norton therefore spent winters studying with some of the best teachers in Albany, New York City, New Haven, and Boston. It was apparently his study of mineralogy which first awakened his interest in natural science. In 1844, he went abroad to study, spending two years at Edinburgh and nine months at Utrecht.
In 1846, Norton was appointed professor of agricultural chemistry at Yale and, together with the younger Benjamin Silliman, founded the department of scientific education which later became the Sheffield Scientific School. When Silliman left Yale for another institution, Norton assumed full responsibility for the new venture.
Despite the strenuous labors involved in directing the new school, Norton's educational influence was not confined to the college classroom. Motivated by a genuine interest in the public welfare and a sympathetic concern for the practical problems of the farmer, he constantly sought to convince the general public of the great practical value of applying scientific methods to agriculture. He contributed numerous articles of a popular nature to the agricultural press, especially to the Albany Cultivator, and he addressed many agricultural societies on various aspects of scientific agriculture.
Norton also wrote a number of scientific papers including: "On the Analysis of the Oat", a prize study made in 1845 while he was still a student and published in 1846; "The Potato Disease" (1846); "Account of Some Researches on the Protein Bodies of Peas and Almonds, and a Body of Somewhat Similar Nature Existing in Oats" (1848); and an essay published in 1850 under the title Elements of Scientific Agriculture, used as a textbook for schools. He also assisted Henry Stephens with additions to The Book of the Farm (published in the U. S. in 1850-1851 as The Farmer's Guide), a detailed description of the labors of the farmer as related to the seasons of the year.
With his promising career scarcely begun, Norton was stricken with illness. The burden of his many activities left him too weak to resist and he died in Farmington, Connecticut, on September 5, 1852, at the age of thirty.
The John Pitkin Norton Papers are divided into three series: CORRESPONDENCE, WRITINGS, and SPECIAL FILES. CORRESPONDENCE contains three subsections. The first, "General Correspondence," contains approximately 85 letters received by John Pitkin Norton from 1848 to 1851. Many of these concern details of the publication of Norton's works, especially his additions to Henry Stephens' Book of the Farm. There are numerous other letters requesting Norton to address various organizations.
The second subsection, "Invoices", consists of one volume containing approximately 135 invoices received by Norton from 1850 to 1852. A list of persons from whom the invoices were received is in the back of the book.
The third subsection, "Letters Written by John Pitkin Norton", consists of one letterbook containing letterpress copies of approximately 75 letters written by Norton in 1851-1852. There are also several letter-essays written for the agricultural press. A list of persons to whom his letters were addressed is in the front of the book.
WRITINGS makes up the bulk of the papers and is divided into: "Addresses," "Articles,'' "Diaries," "Lectures," and "Notes." "Addresses" consists primarily of printed copies of Norton's addresses on scientific agriculture to various agricultural societies. There is also one speech given before the Connecticut Legislature. "Articles" consists of Norton's scientific papers, his additions to Stephens' Book of the Farm ("Winter," "Spring," "Summer," and "Autumn"), and numerous articles contributed to the agricultural press, especially to the Albany Cultivator."Diaries" is composed of ten manuscript volumes covering the years 1838-1847 and 1851-1852, and contain among other topics Norton's observations on slavery and abolition, the Amistad case, the Liberty Party, religion and temperance. "Lectures" consists primarily of a series of 33 lectures used in courses at Yale College from 1847 to 1851. "Notes" contains a catalogue of minerals, a volume containing a subject guide to his readings, and a sheet with notes about various soils.
SPECIAL FILES, contains a daguerreotype, an agricultural and geological map of New York State (1844), a volume containing manuscript copies of poems by various authors, and a scrapbook of newspaper clippings (mostly poems, anecdotes, and short stories.) [For a biographical sketch of John Norton Pitkin see the William Henry Brewer Papers, MS 100.]
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, diaries, writings and other papers of John Pitkin Norton, professor of agricultural chemistry at Yale from 1846-1852. Norton's diaries contain among other topics Norton's observations on slavery and abolition, the Amistad case, the Liberty Party, religion and temperance. Professor Norton was also closely associated with the early days of the Sheffield Scientific School and was a pioneer in the application of scientific principles and methods to agriculture.
Agriculture; Science; Europe -- Description and travel; Agriculturists; Chemists; Scientists; Norton, John Pitkin, 1822-1852; Amistad (Schooner); Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Sheffield Scientific School
- Correspondence, 1848-1852; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is divided into three subsections, as follows:
  "General Correspondence," consisting of letters received by John Pitkin Norton is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer.
  "Invoices," consists of one volume containing invoices received by John Pitkin Norton. A list prepared by Norton of persons from whom invoices were received is at the back of the book.
  "Letters by John Pitkin Norton," consists of one letterbook containing letterpress copies of letters written by Norton. A list prepared by Norton of persons to whom his letters were addressed is in the front of the book. (A small number of letters sent by Norton are in bound letter-books in the "Articles" section of Series II. The correspondence folders are cross referenced to indicate where this material may be found.)
  - General Correspondence
    - A, 1849, 1851, undated
      - Allen, A. A. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Allen, A. B. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Alsof, Charles (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B, 1848-1851, undated
      - Ball, L. Chandler (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Blackwood, R. W. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Blackwood and Sons (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Book of the Farm (memorandum) (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Bosquit, A. E. Dudock (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Brown, Harvey (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Buckland, George (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - C, 1849, 1851
      - Calhoun, W. B. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Campbell, William H. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Chambers, William H. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Chandler, Adoniram (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Chickering, J. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Clark, William (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D-F, 1848-1851
      - Delafield, I. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Elwyn, A. L. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Evans, Gurdon (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Field, Maunsell B. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - G-H, 1849, 1851, undated
      - Goadby, Henry (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Gott and Palmer (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Gould, Augustus A. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Henry, Joseph (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Hickson, Caleb S. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Holbrook, F. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - J-L, 1849
      - Jay, John (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Johnson, B. P. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Johnston, James (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Kirby, E. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Lincoln, John W. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Lowell, John A. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - M-O, 1851
      - Meads, Orlando (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Moffat, Daniel (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Olcott, Thomas W. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - P
      - Paine, N. E. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Pardee, R. G. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Pease, E. H. and Co. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Phelps, Oliver (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Putnam, George P., 1850-1851, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - R Rockwell, Charles H., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sc-Si, 1849-1851
      - Scott, Leonard and Co. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Sheffrey, P. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Sherwood, John W. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Sibbs, Wolcott (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Silliman, Benjamin, Jr. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Sk-St, 1848, 1849, 1851
      - Skinner, I. S. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Slight, James (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Smith, I. Lawrence (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Sprangler, A. M. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Stabler, Edward (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Stafford, James R. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Stephens, Henrh (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - T-W, 1849-1851, undated
      - Tinson, R. U. and Co. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Tucker, Luther (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Völcker, August (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Wendell, Herman (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Wurter, Henry (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Wyman, Morrill (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Invoices
      - A list of persons from whom invoices are received is in the back of the book, 1850-1852 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence From:
      - Norton, John Pitkin, 1851-1852 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Writings, 1837-1852; Series II
  WRITINGS is divided into: "Addresses," "Articles," "Diaries," "Lectures," and "Notes."
  "Articles" are arranged alphabetically by title. Included in this section, under the title "Agricultural Press," are numerous articles written in letter form to agricultural periodicals. (Several additional "Agricultural Press" articles are contained in the bound volume of "Letters by John Pitkin Norton" in Series I). These articles are bound into two volumes, each of which has an index in the front, and one unindexed volume. These three volumes also contain other material; one contains drafts of Norton's additions to Stephens Book of the Farm:"Winter," "Spring," "Summer," and "Autumn." A list of the material in each volume appears on the front of the folders, and folders are cross referenced to indicate where other drafts or complementary material may be found.
  "Diaries" consists of ten manuscript volumes covering the years 1838-1852.
  "Lectures" are also arranged chronologically.
  "Notes" contains three folders arranged alphabetically by category.
  - Addresses
    - 1. Hartford County Agricultural Society, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 2. New York State Agricultural Society, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 3. Connecticut Legislature, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 4. New Haven County Agricultural Society, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 5. Hampshire, Franklin, and Hampden, Agricultural Society, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 6. Ontario Co. Agricultural Society, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 7. Hampden County Agricultural Society, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 8. Unidentified Audience, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Articles
    - "Account of Some Researches on the Protein Bodies of Peas and Almonds and a Body of Somewhat Similar Nature Existing in Oats", 1848 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Agricultural Press, 1844-1852 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
    - Agricultural Press, 1851-1852 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Autumn" (pp. 1-63), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Description of a New Sand-Bath", 1851 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Observations on Soil Analyses", undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "On the Analysis of the Oat", 1845 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "On the Value of Soil Analyses", undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Potato Disease", 1846 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Spring" (plus incomplete second draft) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Summer", undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - ["Winter"] (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Diaries
    - Volume I, Apr 26 - Jun 11, 1838-1839 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Volume II, Jun 11 - Jun 28, 1839-1840 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Volume III, Jun 29 - Sep 15, 1840-1841 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Volume IV, Sep 16 - Oct 20, 1841-1842 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Volume V, Oct 21 - Apr 11, 1842-1844 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Volume VI, Apr 12 - May 8, 1844-1845 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Volume VII, May 8 - Aug 29, 1845-1846 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Volume VIII, Aug 30 - Jun 30, 1846-1847 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Jan 1 - Dec 31, 1851 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Jan 1 - Aug, 1852 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Lectures
    - On Ornithology, 1841 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Yale College, No. 1, Introductory, 1847-1848 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Yale College, 1847-1851 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - II. Distinction Between Organic and Inorganic Bodies (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - III. Characteristic Properties of Organic Substances (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - IV. The Atmosphere and Water (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - V. Compounds of Organic Elements (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - VI. Compounds of Organic Elements (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - VII. Source of Organic Elements of Plants (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - VIII. Structure and Functions of the Plant (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - IX. Structure and Functions of the Plant (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - X. Substances of Which Plants Consist (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - XI. Substances of Which Plants Consist (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - XII. Nitrogenous Substances of Plants (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - XIII. How the Supply of Organic Food Is Retained (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - XIV. Inorganic Constituents of Plants (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - XV. Inorganic Constituents of Plants (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - XVI. Relative Proportions of the Inorganic Substances of Plants (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XVII. Theories of Rotation of Crops (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XVIII. Nature of the Soil (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XIX. Composition of Principal Rocks and Soils (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XX. Mechanical Improvement of Soils (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XXI. Subsoiling and Chemical Improvements (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XXII. Mineral Manures (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XXIII. Inorganic Manures; Lime (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XXIV. Lime; Organic Manures (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XXV. Organic Manures (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - XXVI. Organic Manures (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - XXVII. Animal Manures (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - XXVIII. Products of the Soil (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - XIX. Products of the Soil (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - XXX. Products of the Soil (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - XXXI. Casein and Cheese (Box 6, Folder 34)
      - XXXII. Feeding, Fattening, and [Cheese] (Box 6, Folder 34)
      - XXXIII. Recapitulation and Conclusion (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Yale College, 1850 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - University of Albany, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Notes
    - Catalogue of Minerals, 1841-1842 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Index of Subjects (Notes on Readings), 1837-? (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Soil Notes, Albany, New Haven, Farmington, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Special Files, 1844, undated; Series III
  SPECIAL FILES contains four folders arranged alphabetically by category.
  - Daguerreotype, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Map of New York State, Agricultural and Geological, 1844 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Poems, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook (Box 7, Folder 4)